The President:
Mr. Speaker, Mr. Vice President,
members of
Congress,
my fellow Americans:
Today in America, a
teacher spent extra time
with a student who needed
it,
and did her part to lift
America's graduation rate
to its highest level in more
than three decades.
An entrepreneur flipped
on the lights in her tech
startup, and did her part
to add to the more than
8 million new jobs our
businesses have created
over the past four years.
[Applause]
An autoworker
fine-tuned some
of the best, most fuel-efficient
cars in the world,
and did his part to help America
wean itself
off foreign oil.
A farmer prepared for the
spring after the strongest
five-year stretch of farm
exports in our history.
A rural doctor gave a
young child
the first prescription to treat
asthma
that his mother could afford.
[Applause]
A man took
the bus home
from the graveyard shift,
bone-tired, but dreaming
big dreams for his son.
And in tight-knit
communities all across
America, fathers and
mothers will
tuck in their kids, put an arm
around their spouse,
remember fallen comrades, and
give thanks for being home from
a war that, after 12 long
years,
is finally coming to an end.
[Applause]
Tonight, this chamber
speaks with one voice
to the people we represent:
It is you, our citizens,
who make the state
of our union strong.
[Applause]
And here are the results
of your efforts:
The lowest unemployment
rate in over five years.
[Applause]
A rebounding
housing market.
[Applause] A manufacturing
sector that's adding
jobs for the first time
since the 1990s.
[Applause] More oil
produced at home
than we buy from the rest of the
world --
the first time that's happened
in nearly 20 years.
[Applause] Our deficits
-- cut by more than half.
[Applause] And for the
first time in over a
decade, business leaders
around the world have
declared that China is no
longer
the world's number one place to
invest; America is.
[Applause]
That's why I believe this
can be a breakthrough
year for America.
After five years of grit
and determined effort,
the United States is better
positioned
for the 21st century than any
other nation on Earth.
The question for everyone
in this chamber, running
through every decision we
make this year,
is whether we are going to help
or hinder this progress.
For several years now,
this town has been
consumed by a rancorous
argument over
the proper size of the
federal government.
It's an important debate
-- one that dates back
to our very founding.
But when that debate
prevents us from carrying
out even the most basic
functions of our democracy
-- when our differences
shut down government
or threaten the full faith
and credit of the United
States -- then we are
not doing right
by the American people.
[Applause]
Now, as President, I'm
committed to making
Washington work better,
and rebuilding
the trust of the people
who sent us here.
And I believe most
of you are, too.
Last month, thanks to
the work of Democrats
and Republicans, Congress
finally produced
a budget that undoes some of
last year's severe cuts
to priorities like education.
Nobody got everything they
wanted, and we can still
do more to invest in this
country's future
while bringing down our deficit
in a balanced way,
but the budget compromise should
leave us freer
to focus on creating new jobs,
not creating new crises.
[Applause]
In the coming months,
let's see where else
we can make progress
together.
Let's make this
a year of action.
That's what most Americans
want: for all
of us in this chamber to focus
on their lives,
their hopes, their aspirations.
What I believe unites the
people of this nation --
regardless of race or
region or party,
young or old, rich or poor --
is the simple, profound
belief in opportunity for
all -- the notion that if
you work hard and take
responsibility,
you can get ahead in America.
[Applause]
Let's face it: That belief
has suffered
some serious blows.
Over more than three
decades, even before the
Great Recession hit,
massive shifts in
technology and global
competition
had eliminated a lot of good,
middle-class jobs,
and weakened the economic
foundations
that families depend on.
Today, after four years of
economic growth,
corporate profits and stock
prices have rarely been higher,
and those at the top
have never done better.
But average wages
have barely budged.
Inequality has deepened.
Upward mobility
has stalled.
The cold, hard fact is
that even
in the midst of recovery, too
many Americans are working more
than ever just to get by,
let alone to get ahead.
And too many still
aren't working at all.
So our job is to
reverse these trends.
It won't happen right
away,
and we won't agree on everything.
But what I offer tonight
is a set of concrete,
practical proposals
to speed up growth,
strengthen the middle
class,
and build new ladders of
opportunity
into the middle class.
Some require congressional
action,
and I am eager to work with all of you.
But America does not stand
still --
and neither will I.
[Applause] So wherever and
whenever I can take steps
without legislation to
expand opportunity
for more American families,
that's
what I'm going to do.
[Applause]
As usual, our First Lady
sets a good example.
[Applause]
Michelle's
Let's Move partnership
with schools, businesses,
local leaders has helped
bring down childhood
obesity rates
for the first time in 30 years.
[Applause] And that's
an achievement
that will improve lives and
reduce health
care costs for decades to come.
The Joining Forces
alliance that Michelle and
Jill Biden launched
has already encouraged
employers to hire or train
nearly 400,000 veterans and military spouses.
[Applause]
Taking a page from that
playbook,
the White House just organized a
College Opportunity Summit,
where already, 150 universities,
businesses,
nonprofits have made concrete
commitments to reduce
inequality in access to
higher education --
and to help every hardworking
kid go to college and succeed
when they get to campus.
[Applause]
And across the country,
we're partnering with mayors,
governors, and state
legislatures on issues from
homelessness
to marriage equality.
The point is there are
millions of Americans
outside of Washington
who are tired
of stale political arguments and
are moving
this country forward.
They believe, and I
believe,
that here in America, our
success should depend
not on accident of birth, but
the strength of our work ethic
and the scope
of our dreams.
That's what drew
our forebears here.
It's how the daughter of
a factory worker
is CEO of America's largest
automaker.
[Applause]
How the son of a barkeep
is Speaker of the House.
[Applause]
How the son of a single mom can
be President of the greatest nation on Earth.
[Applause]
Opportunity is who we are.
And the defining project
of our generation must
be to restore that promise.
We know where to start:
The best measure
of opportunity is
access to a good job.
With the economy picking
up speed,
companies say they intend to
hire more people this year.
And over half of big
manufacturers
say they're thinking of
insourcing jobs from abroad.
[Applause]
So let's make that
decision easier
for more companies.
Both Democrats and
Republicans have argued
that our tax code is
riddled with wasteful,
complicated loopholes
that punish businesses
investing here and reward
companies
that keep profits abroad.
Let's flip that equation.
Let's work together to
close those loopholes,
end those incentives to ship
jobs overseas,
and lower tax rates for
businesses
that create jobs right here at home.
[Applause]
Moreover, we can take the
money we save from
this transition to tax reform
to create jobs rebuilding
our roads, upgrading our ports,
unclogging our commutes --
because in today's global
economy, first-class jobs
gravitate
to first-class infrastructure.
We'll need Congress
to protect more than 3 million
jobs by finishing
transportation
and waterways bills
this summer.
[Applause]
That can happen.
But I'll act on my own
to slash bureaucracy
and streamline the permitting
process for key projects,
so we can get more
construction workers
on the job as fast
as possible.
[Applause]
We also have the chance,
right now, to beat other
countries in the race for
the next wave
of high-tech manufacturing jobs.
My administration has
launched two hubs
for high-tech manufacturing
in Raleigh, North Carolina and Youngstown, Ohio,
where we've connected businesses
to research universities that
can help America lead the world
in advanced technologies.
Tonight, I'm announcing
we'll launch
six more this year.
Bipartisan bills in both
houses could double
the number of these hubs and
the jobs they create.
So get those bills to my
desk;
put more Americans back to work.
[Applause]
Let's do more to help the
entrepreneurs and small
business owners who create
most new jobs in America.
Over the past five years,
my administration has made
more loans to small
business owners
than any other.
And when 98 percent of
our exporters
are small businesses, new trade
partnerships
with Europe and the Asia Pacific will
help them create more jobs.
We need to work together
on tools like bipartisan
Trade Promotion Authority
to protect our workers,
protect our environment,
and open new markets
to new goods stamped
"Made in the USA."
[Applause]
Listen, China and Europe
aren't standing
on the sidelines, and
neither should we.
We know that the nation
that goes
all-in on innovation today will
own the global economy tomorrow.
This is an edge America
cannot surrender.
Federally funded research
helped
lead to the ideas and inventions
behind Google and smartphones.
And that's why Congress
should undo the damage
done by last year's cuts
to basic research
so we can unleash the next
great American discovery.
[Applause]
There are entire
industries to be built
based on vaccines
that stay ahead
of drug-resistant bacteria,
or paper-thin material
that's stronger
than steel.
And let's pass a patent
reform bill that allows
our businesses to stay
focused on innovation,
not costly and needless
litigation.
[Applause]
Now, one of the biggest
factors
in bringing more jobs back is
our commitment
to American energy.
The all-of-the-above
energy strategy
I announced a few years ago
is working, and today,
America is closer to
energy independence
than we have been in decades.
[Applause]
One of the reasons why
is natural gas
-- if extracted safely, it's the
bridge fuel that
can power our economy with less
of the carbon pollution that
causes climate change.
Businesses plan to invest
almost $100 billion
in new factories that
use natural gas.
I'll cut red tape to help
states get those factories
built and put folks to
work,
and this Congress can help by
putting people
to work building fueling
stations that shift more
cars and trucks
from foreign oil to
American natural gas.
[Applause]
Meanwhile, my
administration will
keep working with the industry
to sustain production
and jobs growth while
strengthening protection
of our air, our water,
our communities.
And while we're at it,
I'll use my authority
to protect more of our
pristine federal lands
for future generations.
[Applause]
It's not just oil and
natural gas production
that's booming; we're
becoming
a global leader in solar, too.
Every four minutes,
another American home
or business goes solar, every
panel pounded
into place by a worker whose job
cannot be outsourced.
Let's continue that
progress with a smarter
tax policy that stops
giving $4 billion a year
to fossil fuel industries
that don't need it,
so we can invest more in fuels
of the future that do.
[Applause]
And even as we've
increased energy
production, we've
partnered with businesses,
builders, and local
communities
to reduce the energy we consume.
When we rescued our
automakers, for example,
we worked with them to
set
higher fuel efficiency standards for our cars.
In the coming months, I'll
build on that success
by setting new standards for
our trucks,
so we can keep driving down oil
imports
and what we pay at the pump.
And taken together, our
energy policy is creating
jobs and leading to a
cleaner, safer planet.
Over the past eight years,
the United States
has reduced our total carbon
pollution more than any
other nation on Earth.
[Applause]
But we have to
act with more urgency --
because a changing climate
is already
harming Western communities
struggling with drought,
and coastal cities dealing
with floods.
That's why I directed my
administration
to work with states, utilities,
and others to set new
standards on the amount of
carbon pollution
our power plants are allowed
to dump into the air.
[Applause]
The shift to a cleaner
energy economy won't
happen overnight, and it
will require
some tough choices along the way.
But the debate is settled.
Climate change is a fact.
[Applause] And when our
children's children
look us in the eye and ask if
we did all we could
to leave them a safer, more
stable world,
with new sources of energy, I want
us to be able to say yes, we did.
[Applause]
Finally, if we're serious
about economic growth,
it is time to heed the call
of business leaders,
labor leaders, faith leaders,
law enforcement --
and fix our broken
immigration system.
[Applause] Republicans and
Democrats
in the Senate have acted.
And I know that members of
both parties
in the House want to do the same.
Independent economists say
immigration reform
will grow our economy and
shrink our deficits by
almost $1 trillion in
the next two decades.
And for good reason:
When people come here
to fulfill their dreams -- to
study, invent,
contribute to our culture --
they make our country
a more attractive place for
businesses to locate and
create jobs for everybody.
So let's get immigration
reform done this year.
[Applause]
Let's
get it done.
It's time.
[Applause]
The ideas I've outlined
so far can speed up growth
and create more jobs.
But in this rapidly
changing economy,
we have to make sure that every
American has the skills
to fill those jobs.
The good news is we
know how to do it.
Two years ago, as the
auto industry came roaring
back, Andra Rush opened
up a manufacturing firm in Detroit.
She knew that Ford needed
parts for the best-selling
truck in America, and she
knew how
to make those parts.
She just needed
the workforce.
So she dialed up what
we call
an American Jobs Center, places
where folks can walk
in to get the help or training
they need to find
a new job or a better job.
She was flooded
with new workers.
And today, Detroit
Manufacturing Systems
has more than 700 employees.
And what Andra and her
employees experienced
is how it should be for every
employer
and every job seeker.
So tonight, I've asked
Vice President Biden
to lead an across-the-board
reform of America's
training programs to
make sure
they have one mission: Train
Americans with the skills
employers need, and match them
to good jobs that need
to be filled right now.
[Applause]
That means more on-the-job
training and more
apprenticeships that set a
young worker
on an upward trajectory for life.
It means connecting
companies
to community colleges that can
help design training
to fill their specific needs.
And if Congress wants to
help,
you can concentrate funding on
proven programs that connect
more ready-to-work Americans
with ready-to-be-filled jobs.
I'm also convinced we can
help Americans return
to the workforce faster by
reforming unemployment
insurance so that it's
more effective
in today's economy.
But first, this Congress
needs to restore
the unemployment insurance you
just let expire
for 1.6 million people.
[Applause]
Let me tell you why.
Misty DeMars is a mother
of two young boys.
She'd been steadily
employed since
she was a teenager, put herself
through college.
She'd never collected
unemployment benefits,
but she'd been paying taxes.
In May, she and her
husband
used their life savings to buy
their first home.
A week later, budget cuts
claimed the job she loved.
Last month, when their
unemployment
insurance was cut off, she sat
down and wrote me a letter,
the kind I get every day.
"We are the face of the
unemployment crisis," she wrote.
"I'm not dependent
on the government.
Our country depends on
people like
us who build careers, contribute
to society,
care about our neighbors.
I'm confident that in time
I will find a job,
I will pay my taxes, and we will
raise our children
in their own home in the
community we love.
Please give us
this chance."
Congress, give these
hardworking, responsible
Americans that chance.
[Applause]
Give them that chance.
Give them the chance.
[Applause]
They need our
help right now.
But more important, this
country needs
them in the game.
That's why I've been
asking CEOs
to give more long-term
unemployed workers
a fair shot at new jobs, a new
chance
to support their families.
And in fact, this week,
many will come
to the White House to make
that commitment real.
Tonight, I ask every
business leader in America
to join us and to do the
same --
because we are stronger when
America fields a full team.
[Applause]
Of course, it's not
enough
to train today's workforce.
We also have to prepare
tomorrow's workforce,
by guaranteeing every child
access
to a world-class education.
[Applause]
Estiven Rodriguez couldn't
speak a word of English
when he moved to New
York City at age nine.
But last month, thanks
to the support
of great teachers and an
innovative tutoring program,
he led a march of his classmates
through a crowd
of cheering parents and
neighbors
from their high school to the
post office,
where they mailed off their
college applications.
And this son of a factory
worker just found
out he's going to college
this fall.
[Applause]
Five years ago, we set out
to change
the odds for all our kids.
We worked with lenders to
reform student loans,
and today, more young people
are earning college
degrees than ever before.
Race to the Top, with the
help of governors
from both parties, has helped
states
raise expectations and performance.
Teachers and principals in
schools from Tennessee
to Washington, D.C. are
making big strides
in preparing students with
the skills
for the new economy
-- problem solving, critical thinking,
science, technology, engineering, math.
Some of this
change is hard.
It requires everything
from more challenging
curriculums and more
demanding parents
to better support for
teachers and new ways
to measure how well our kids
think,
not how well they can fill in a
bubble on a test.
But it is worth it
and it is working.
The problem is we're still
not reaching enough kids,
and we're not
reaching them in time.
And that has to change.
Research shows that one
of the best investments
we can make in a child's
life
is high-quality early education.
[Applause]
Last year, I
asked this
Congress to help states make
high-quality
pre-K available to
every 4-year-old.
And as a parent as well as
a President,
I repeat that request tonight.
But in the meantime, 30
states have raised
pre-k funding on their own.
They know we can't wait.
So just as we worked
with states to reform
our schools, this year we'll
invest
in new partnerships with states
and communities across
the country in a Race to
the
Top for our youngest children.
And as Congress decides
what it's going
to do, I'm going to pull
together a coalition
of elected officials, business
leaders,
and philanthropists willing to
help more kids
access the high-quality pre-K
that they need.
[Applause]
It is right for America. We need to get this done.
Last year, I also pledged
to connect 99 percent
of our students to high-speed
broadband
over the next four years.
Tonight, I can announce
that
with the support of the FCC and
companies like Apple, Microsoft,
Sprint, and Verizon, we've got
a down payment
to start connecting more than
15,000 schools
and 20 million students over the
next two years,
without adding a dime
to the deficit.
[Applause]
We're working to redesign
high schools and partner
them with colleges and
employers that offer
the real-world education and
hands-on training
that can lead directly to
a job and career.
We're shaking up our
system of higher education
to give parents more
information and colleges
more incentives to offer
better value,
so that no middle-class kid is
priced
out of a college education.
We're offering millions
the opportunity
to cap their monthly student
loan payments to 10 percent
of their income, and I want
to work with Congress
to see how we can help even
more Americans
who feel trapped by
student loan debt.
[Applause]
And I'm reaching out to some of
America's
leading foundations and corporations
on a new
initiative to help more
young men of color facing
especially tough odds
to stay on track and reach
their full potential.
The bottom line is
Michelle and I want
every child to have the same
chance
this country gave us.
But we know our
opportunity agenda won't
be complete -- and too
many young people
entering the workforce today
will see the American Dream
as an empty promise -- unless
we also do more
to make sure our economy honors
the dignity of work,
and hard work pays off for
every single American.
Today, women make up about
half our workforce,
but they still make 77 cents
for every dollar
a man earns.
That is wrong, and
in 2014,
it's an embarrassment.
Women deserve equal
pay for equal work.
[Applause]
She deserves to have a baby without sacrificing her job.
A mother deserves a day
off to care for
a sick child or a sick parent
without
running into hardship.
[Applause] And you know
what, a father does, too.
It is time to do away with
workplace policies
that belong in a "Mad
Men" episode.
[Laughter]
[Applause]
This year, let's all come together -- Congress,
the White House, businesses from
Wall Street to Main Street --
to give every woman the
opportunity she deserves.
[Applause]
Because
I believe when women
succeed, America succeeds.
[Applause]
Now, women hold a majority
of lower-wage jobs,
but they're not the only ones
stifled by stagnant wages.
Americans understand that
some people
will earn more money than
others, and we don't resent
those who, by virtue of their
efforts, achieve incredible success.
That's what America
is all about.
But Americans
overwhelmingly agree that
no one who works full-time
should ever have
to raise a family in poverty.
[Applause]
In the year since I asked
this Congress to raise the
minimum wage, five states
have passed
laws to raise theirs.
Many businesses have
done it on their own.
Nick Chute is here today
with his boss, John Soranno.
John's an owner of Punch
Pizza in Minneapolis,
and Nick helps make the dough.
[Laughter] Only now
he makes more of it.
[Laughter] John just gave
his employees a raise,
to 10 bucks an hour -- and
that's a decision
that has eased their financial
stress and boosted their morale.
Tonight, I ask more of
America's business leaders
to follow John's lead: Do
what you can to raise
your employees' wages.
[Applause]
It's good
for the economy.
It's good for America.
[Applause]
To every mayor,
governor, state legislator
in America, I say you
don't have to wait
for Congress to act --
Americans will support
you if you take this on.
And as a chief executive,
I intend
to lead by example.
Profitable corporations
like Costco see higher
wages as the smart way
to boost productivity
and reduce turnover.
We should too.
In the coming weeks, I
will issue an executive
order requiring federal
contractors
to pay their federally funded
employees a fair wage
of at least $10.10 an hour --
because if you cook our troops'
meals or wash their
dishes,
you should not have to live in poverty.
[Applause]
Of course, to reach
millions more, Congress
does need to get on board.
Today, the federal minimum
wage is worth about
20 percent less than it was
when
Ronald Reagan first stood here.
And Tom Harkin and George
Miller have a bill
to fix that by lifting the
minimum wage to $10.10.
It's easy to
remember, $10.10.
This will help families.
It will give businesses
customers with
more money to spend.
It does not involve any
new bureaucratic program.
So join the rest
of the country.
Say yes.
Give America a raise.
[Applause]
Give them a raise.
There are other steps we
can take to help families
make ends meet, and few
are more effective
at reducing inequality and
helping families pull
themselves up through
hard work than
the Earned Income Tax Credit.
Right now, it helps about
half
of all parents at some point.
Think about that -- it
helps about half
of all parents in America at
some point in their lives.
But I agree with
Republicans like
Senator Rubio that it doesn't do
enough for single workers
who don't have kids.
So let's work together
to strengthen the credit,
reward work, help more
Americans get ahead.
Let's do more to help
Americans
save for retirement.
Today, most workers
don't have a pension.
A Social Security check
often isn't
enough on its own.
And while the stock market
has doubled
over the last five years, that
doesn't help folks
who don't have 401(k)s.
That's why, tomorrow, I
will direct
the Treasury to create a new way
for working Americans
to start their own retirement
savings: MyRA.
It's a new savings bond
that encourages
folks to build a nest egg.
MyRA guarantees a decent
return with no risk of
losing what you put in.
And if this Congress wants
to help, work with
me to fix an upside-down tax
code that gives
big tax breaks to help the
wealthy save,
but does little or nothing for
middle-class Americans.
Offer every American
access to an automatic
IRA on the job, so they can
save at work
just like everyone in this
chamber can.
And since the most
important investment
many families make is their
home, send me legislation
that protects taxpayers
from footing
the bill for a housing crisis
ever again,
and keeps the dream of
homeownership
alive for future generations.
[Applause]
One last point on
financial security:
For decades, few things
exposed hardworking
families to economic
hardship more
than a broken health care system.
And in case you haven't
heard,
we're in the process of fixing that.
[Applause]
A preexisting condition used
to mean that someone like Amanda
Shelley,
a physician's assistant and
single mom from Arizona,
couldn't get health insurance.
But on January 1st,
she got covered.
[Applause]
On January 3rd, she felt a sharp pain.
On January 6th, she
had emergency surgery.
Just one week earlier,
Amanda said,
that surgery would have meant
bankruptcy.
That's what health
insurance reform
is all about -- the peace of
mind that if misfortune
strikes, you don't have
to lose everything.
Already, because of the
Affordable Care Act,
more than 3 million Americans
under age 26 have gained
coverage under their
parents' plans.
[Applause]
More than 9
million Americans
have signed up for private
health insurance
or Medicaid coverage.
[Applause]
Nine million.
And here's another
number: zero.
Because of this law, no
American -- none --
zero -- can ever again be
dropped or denied coverage
for a preexisting
condition like asthma,
or back pain, or cancer.
[Applause]
No woman can
ever be charged more
just because she's a woman.
[Applause]
And we did all
this while adding years
to Medicare's finances,
keeping Medicare premiums
flat, and lowering
prescription costs
for millions of seniors.
Now, I do not expect to
convince
my Republican friends on the
merits of this law.
[Laughter]
But I know
that the American people
are not interested in
refighting old battles.
So, again, if you have
specific plans
to cut costs, cover more people,
increase choice --
tell America what you'd
do differently.
Let's see if the
numbers add up.
But let's not have another
40-something votes
to repeal a law that's
already helping
millions of Americans like Amanda.
[Applause]
The first 40 were plenty.
We all owe it to the
American people
to say what we're for, not
just what we're against.
And if you want to know
the real impact this law
is having, just talk to
Governor Steve Beshear
of Kentucky, who's
here tonight.
Now Kentucky is not the
most liberal
part of the country.
[Laughter]
That's not
where
I got my highest vote totals.
[Laughter]
But he's like
a man possessed
when it comes to covering his
commonwealth's families.
They are our neighbors
and our friends, he said.
"They're people we shop
and go to church with,
farmers out on the
tractor, grocery clerks.
They're people who go to
work every morning
praying they don't get sick.
No one deserves
to live that way."
Steve is right.
That's why, tonight, I ask
every American
who knows someone without health
insurance to help them get
covered by March 31st.
[Applause]
Help them get covered.
Moms, get on
your kids to sign up.
Kids, call your mom and
walk
her through the application.
It will give her some
peace of mind --
plus, she'll appreciate
hearing from you.
[Laughter]
After all, that's the
spirit that has always
moved this nation forward.
It's the spirit of
citizenship --
the recognition that
through hard work
and responsibility, we can
pursue our individual
dreams but still come
together
as one American family to make
sure the next generation
can pursue its dreams as well.
Citizenship means standing
up for everyone's
right to vote.
[Applause]
Last year, part
of the Voting Rights Act
was weakened, but
conservative Republicans
and liberal Democrats
are working together
to strengthen it.
And the bipartisan
commission I appointed,
chaired by my campaign
lawyer and Governor
Romney's campaign lawyer,
came together and have
offered reforms so that no
one has to wait
more than a half hour to vote.
Let's support
these efforts.
[Applause]
It should be
the power of our vote,
not the size of our bank
accounts
that drives our democracy.
[Applause]
Citizenship means standing
up for the lives
that gun violence steals
from us each day.
I've seen the courage
of parents, students,
pastors, police officers
all over this country
who say "we are not afraid."
And I intend to keep
trying,
with or without Congress, to
help stop more tragedies
from visiting innocent
Americans
in our movie theaters, in our
shopping malls,
or schools like Sandy Hook.
[Applause]
Citizenship demands a
sense of common purpose;
participation in the hard
work of self-government;
an obligation to
serve our communities.
And I know this chamber
agrees that few Americans
give more to their country
than our diplomats
and the men and women of the
United States Armed Forces.
[Applause]
Tonight, because of the
extraordinary troops
and civilians who risk and lay
down their lives
to keep us free, the United
States is more secure.
When I took office, nearly
180,000 Americans
were serving in Iraq
and Afghanistan.
Today, all our troops
are out of Iraq.
More than 60,000 of our
troops have already come
home from Afghanistan.
With Afghan forces now
in the lead for their
own security, our troops have
moved to a support role.
Together with our allies,
we will complete
our mission there by the
end of this year,
and America's longest war
will finally be over.
[Applause]
After 2014, we will
support a unified
Afghanistan as it takes
responsibility
for its own future.
If the Afghan government
signs a security agreement
that we have negotiated,
a small force of Americans
could remain in
Afghanistan with NATO
allies to carry out two
narrow missions: training
and assisting
Afghan forces,
and counterterrorism
operations
to pursue any remnants of al Qaeda.
For while our relationship
with Afghanistan
will change, one thing will
not: our resolve
that terrorists do not launch
attacks
against our country.
[Applause]
The fact is that
danger remains.
While we put al Qaeda's
core leadership
on a path to defeat, the threat
has evolved as al Qaeda
affiliates and other
extremists take root
in different parts
of the world.
In Yemen, Somalia, Iraq,
Mali, we have
to keep working with partners to
disrupt
and disable those networks.
In Syria, we'll support
the opposition that
rejects the agenda of
terrorist networks.
Here at home, we'll
keep strengthening
our defenses, and combat new
threats like cyberattacks.
And as we reform our
defense budget,
we will have to keep faith with
our men and women
in uniform, and invest in the
capabilities
they need to succeed in
future missions.
[Applause]
We have to
remain vigilant.
But I strongly believe
our leadership
and our security cannot depend
on our outstanding military alone.
As Commander-in-Chief,
I have used force when
needed to protect the
American people,
and I will never hesitate to do
so as long
as I hold this office.
But I will not send our
troops into harm's way
unless it is truly
necessary,
nor will I allow our sons and
daughters to be mired
in open-ended conflicts.
We must fight the battles
that need to be fought,
not those that terrorists
prefer from us --
large-scale deployments
that drain our strength
and may ultimately
feed extremism.
So even as we actively
and aggressively pursue
terrorist networks --
through more targeted
efforts and by building
the capacity
of our foreign partners --
America must move
off a permanent war footing.
[Applause]
That's why I've
imposed prudent limits
on the use of drones -- for
we will not be safer
if people abroad believe
we strike within their
countries without regard
for the consequence.
That's why, working with
this Congress,
I will reform our surveillance
programs,
because the vital work of our
intelligence community
depends on public
confidence,
here and abroad, that privacy of
ordinary people
is not being violated.
[Applause]
And with the Afghan war
ending, this needs
to be the year Congress lifts
the remaining restrictions
on detainee transfers and
we close the prison
at Guantanamo Bay --
[applause]
because we counter terrorism not
just through intelligence
and military actions, but
by remaining true
to our constitutional ideals,
and setting an example
for the rest of the world.
[Applause]
You see, in a world of
complex threats,
our security, our leadership
depends
on all elements of our power,
including
strong and principled diplomacy.
American diplomacy has
rallied more
than 50 countries to prevent
nuclear materials from
falling into the wrong
hands, and allowed
us to reduce our own reliance
on Cold War stockpiles.
American diplomacy, backed
by the threat of force,
is why Syria's chemical
weapons
are being eliminated.
[Applause]
And we will continue
to work with
the international community
to usher in the future
the Syrian people deserve
-- a future free
of dictatorship,
terror and fear.
As we speak, American
diplomacy
is supporting the Israelis and
Palestinians as they
engage in the difficult
but necessary talks
to end the conflict there; to
achieve dignity
and an independent state for
Palestinians,
and lasting peace and security
for the State of Israel --
a Jewish state that knows
America will
always be at their side.
[Applause]
And it is American
diplomacy,
backed by pressure, that has
halted the progress of Iran's
nuclear program and rolled
back parts of that program
for the very first
time in a decade.
As we gather here
tonight,
Iran has begun to eliminate its
stockpile of higher
levels of enriched uranium.
It's not installing
advanced centrifuges.
Unprecedented inspections
help the world verify
every day that Iran is
not building a bomb.
And with our allies and
partners, we're engaged
in negotiations to see if we
can peacefully achieve
a goal we all share:
preventing
Iran from obtaining a
nuclear weapon.
[Applause]
These negotiations
will be difficult.
They may not succeed.
We are clear-eyed about
Iran's support
for terrorist organizations
like Hezbollah,
which threatens our allies.
And we're clear about
the mistrust between
our nations, mistrust that
cannot be wished away.
But these negotiations
don't rely on trust.
Any long-term deal we
agree to must
be based on verifiable action
that convinces
us and the international
community that Iran
is not building a nuclear bomb.
If John F. Kennedy and
Ronald Reagan
could negotiate
with the Soviet Union, then
surely a strong and confident
America can negotiate with
less powerful adversaries today.
[Applause]
The sanctions that we put
in place helped make
this opportunity possible.
But let me be clear: I
this Congress sends
me a new sanctions bill now
that threatens
to derail these talks, I
will veto it.
[Applause]
For the sake of
our national security,
we must give diplomacy
a chance to succeed.
[Applause]
If Iran's
leaders do not seize this
opportunity, then I will
be the first to call
for more sanctions, and stand
ready to exercise
all options to make sure Iran
does not build
a nuclear weapon.
But if Iran's leaders do
seize the chance --
and we'll know soon enough --
then Iran could
take an important step to rejoin
the community of nations,
and we will have resolved
one of the leading
security challenges of our
time without
the risks of war.
And, finally, let's
remember that
our leadership is defined
not just
by our defense against threats,
but by the enormous
opportunities to do good
and promote understanding
around the globe --
to forge greater cooperation,
to expand new markets, to free
people from fear and want.
And no one is better
positioned
to take advantage
of those opportunities than America.
Our alliance with Europe
remains the strongest
the world has ever known.
From Tunisia to Burma,
we're supporting those
who are willing to do the
hard work
of building democracy.
In Ukraine, we stand for
the principle
that all people have the right
to express themselves freely
and peacefully, and
to have
a say in their country's future.
Across Africa, we're
bringing together
businesses and governments
to double access
to electricity and help
end extreme poverty.
In the Americas, we're
building new ties
of commerce, but we're also
expanding cultural
and educational exchanges
among young people.
And we will continue to
focus on the Asia Pacific,
where we support our
allies,
shape a future of greater
security and prosperity,
and extend a hand to those
devastated by disaster --
as we did in the Philippines,
when our Marines and civilians
rushed to aid those
battered by a typhoon,
and who were greeted with
words like,
"We will never forget your
kindness" and
"God bless America."
We do these things because
they help promote
our long-term security, and we
do them because we believe
in the inherent dignity
and equality of every
human being, regardless of
race or religion,
creed or sexual orientation.
And next week, the world
will see one expression
of that commitment -- when
Team USA marches the red,
white, and blue into
the Olympic Stadium,
and brings home the gold.
[Applause]
Audience: USA!
USA!
The President: My fellow
Americans, no other
country in the world
does what we do.
On every issue, the world
turns
to us, not simply because of the
size of our economy
or our military might, but
because of the ideals we stand
for and the burdens we bear
to advance them.
No one knows this better
than those
who serve in uniform.
As this time of war
draws to a close,
a new generation of heroes
returns to civilian life.
We'll keep slashing that
backlog
so our veterans receive the
benefits they've earned,
and our wounded warriors receive
the health care --
including the mental
health care
-- that they need.
[Applause]
We'll keep
working to help
all our veterans translate their
skills
and leadership into jobs here at home.
And we will all continue
to join forces
to honor and support our
remarkable military families.
Let me tell you about one
of those families
I've come to know.
I first met Cory Remsburg,
a proud Army Ranger,
at Omaha Beach on the 65th
anniversary of D-Day.
Along with some of his
fellow Rangers,
he walked me through the program
and the ceremony.
He was a strong,
impressive young man,
had an easy manner, he
was sharp as a tack.
And we joked around and
took pictures,
and I told him to stay in touch.
A few months later, on his
tenth deployment,
Cory was nearly killed by a
massive roadside
bomb in Afghanistan.
His comrades found him
in a canal,
face down, underwater, shrapnel
in his brain.
For months, he
lay in a coma.
And the next time I met
him, in the hospital,
he couldn't speak,
could barely move.
Over the years, he's
endured dozens
of surgeries and procedures,
hours
of grueling rehab every day.
Even now, Cory is still
blind in one eye,
still struggles on
his left side.
But slowly, steadily, with
the support of caregivers
like his dad, Craig, and
the community around him,
Cory has grown stronger.
And, day by day, he's
learned to speak again
and stand again
and walk again.
And he's working toward
the day when
he can serve his country again.
"My recovery has not
been easy," he says.
"Nothing in life that's
worth anything is easy."
Cory is here tonight.
And like the Army he
loves, like the America
he serves, Sergeant First
Class Cory Remsburg never
gives up, and he
does not quit.
[Applause]
My fellow Americans, men
and women like Cory
remind us that America has
never come easy.
Our freedom, our
democracy,
has never been easy.
Sometimes we stumble,
we make mistakes;
we get frustrated or discouraged.
But for more than 200
years, we have put those
things aside and placed
our collective shoulder
to the wheel of progress --
to create and build
and expand the possibilities
of individual achievement;
to free other nations
from tyranny and fear;
to promote justice, and
fairness, and equality
under the law so that the
words set to paper
by our founders are made real
for every citizen.
The America we want for
our kids --
a rising America where honest
work is plentiful
and communities are strong;
where prosperity is widely
shared and opportunity for
all lets
us go as far as our dreams and
toil will take us --
none of it is easy.
But if we work together --
if we summon what
is best in us, the way Cory
summoned what is best
in him, with our feet planted
firmly in today
but our eyes cast toward
tomorrow --
I know it is within our reach.
Believe it.
God bless you, and God
bless
the United States of America.
[Applause]